Mss.B.Sh35
American Philosophical Society
William Sharswood papers, 1865-1867
Mss.B.Sh35
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet Ca. 100 items
These papers pertain to minerals and mining, publications, his play "The Betrothed," St. John's College in Maryland, and Reconstruction in South Carolina.
Ca. 100 items.
Sharswood, William, 1836-1905
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Frances Lichten and accessioned, 03/23/1959 (1959 494ms).
Biographical/Historical note
William Sharswood (1836-1905) was a chemist, naturalist and playwright. Born in Philadelphia, Sharswood was the son of William and Agnes Sharswood, and cousin of Pennsylvania Supreme Court Chief Justice George Sharswood (1810-1883, APS 1851). After graduating from the University of Pennsylvania in 1856, Sharswood studied Chemistry at the University of Saxony and received a Ph.D. in 1859.
As a naturalist, Sharswood contributed articles to a number of journals, including Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Linnaea Entomologica, and the Bulletin de la société géologique de Francethe and gave papers at the Boston Society of Natural History and the Elliott Society of Natural History. He also corresponded widely with other American naturalists. Among his major correspondents were John LeConte (1818-1891, APS 1873), John Lawrence LeConte (1825-1883, APS 1853), and Samuel S. Haldeman (1812-1880, APS 1844).
Sharswood also took an interest in Reconstruction in South Carolina and corresponded in 1866 with James D. B. DeBow, the editor of DeBow’s Review, who had advocated an expansion of southern agriculture and commerce. According to the Charlotte Observer, which reported Sharswood’s death in 1905, he lived in North Carolina for the last twenty-five years of his life, and for several years “edited with ability” a newspaper in Stokes County. The January 1902 issue of Publications of the Southern History Association reported that Sharswood was preparing a work for publication, entitled Facts Worth Knowing About North Carolina, which included half tone portraits of “representative” native North Carolinians.
Sharswood died on February 17, 1905 in Winston-Salem, North Carolina as a result of a train accident.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes letters written to William Sharswood in Philadelphia. The material is dated from 1865 to 1867. With the exception of the letters by Bianconi (in Latin), A. R. Rungabes(?) (in French), and the Bayrische Staatsbibliothek (in German), the material is in English.
Since the collection does not include letters written by Sharswood, it offers only limited insight into his own views and activities. Several of the items in this collection deal with matters related to natural history. Sharswood’s correspondents who write about this topic include Samuel Haldeman and Edward Borden. A letter by Haldeman, for example, notes that “human bodies properly interred are not devoured by worms” (3 March 1865); Borden’s letters focus on mineralogy. A few additional letters refer to publications, including the one by Jay (27 March 1865).
In addition, several items relate to Sharswood’s ultimately futile quest to obtain a professorship at St. John’s College in Maryland. Some of the letters discuss related professional pursuits, including Sharswood’s educational plans. Haldeman and Browne, for example, comment on the proposal to have a college for chemistry alone (21 September 1867; 7 November 1867), and LeConte writes in detail about the “University System” to which he had “devoted considerable thought” (22 September 1867).
Material related to Sharswood as a playwright includes the letter by Jay (26 June 1865) and the one by James Pearce (24 February 1866). Two letters refer to Sharswood’s present of his play The Betrothed to the King of Bavaria, including the one from the U.S. Consulate in Munich, signed by Toomy (13 November 1867), and the letter from the king’s secretary (29 November 1867). A few letters, such as the ones from Mitchell and Crowell, concern personal affairs, including the death of Sharswood’s father. The letters by the actress Jean Hosmer tend to be personal and playful; on one accosion, for example, she writes about a perfumed lock of hair she sent Sharswood (5 March 1866).
Of particular interest is a group of letters that deal with the impact of General Sherman's march through South Carolina. Several of these letters were written by John LeConte of Columbia, South Carolina. They are highly critical of Reconstruction. They not only detail the destruction left by Sherman but also discuss the “depth of gloom" which shrouds the future of the state (1 September 1867). LeConte laments the destruction caused by Sherman (the “American Attila”) that left “this once beautiful city” of Columbia, SC, “in ashes.” He was particularly upset that most of the local libraries were “either pallaged or destroyed” (29 August 1865). Another letter refers to the “impoverished condition in which [the people] were left by the invasion of the Vandals.” LeConte argues for the abolition of the Freedmen’s Bureau (25 January 1866) and the disenfranchisement of freedmen (1 September 1867). Mary Graham of South Carolina similarly complains about the destruction of her papers by Sherman's Army (19 June 1866), and Josephine LeConte laments the passing of the “days of Elegant leisure which was so characteristic of Southern life” (25 June 1866). The two brief letters by DeBow relate to DeBow’s decision not to publish Sharswood’s article, the topic of which is not mentioned.
Allen, George, 1808-1876; Allibone, S. Austin (Samuel Austin), 1816-1889; Barden, Edward E.; Boker, George H., (George Henry), 1823-1890; Browne, J. Ross, (John Ross), 1821-1875; DeBow, James D. B.; Everett, William, 1839-1910; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1822-1908; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890; Jackson, Charles T., (Charles Thomas), 1805-1880; Le Conte, John L. (John Lawrence), 1825-1883; Le Conte, John.; St. John's College (Annapolis, Md.); Education.; Mineralogy.; Reconstruction.; South Carolina -- History -- 1865-
- Correspondence
  - Letter to W[illiam] Sharswood, Jan. 18, 1865; 7-3/4x5; Mitchell, J. G.
    Scope and Contents note
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Sorrow at the death of his father.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Feb. 17, 1865; 8x5; Fish, Asa I. (Asa Israel), 1820-1879
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Will discuss problem over tea. Mentions Shakespeare Society.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Feb. 18, 1865; 9-1/2x6; Sanborn, Francis G.
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Asks that his collection of curculionidae be returned. Refers to J.L.LeConte
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Feb. 26, 1865; 8x5; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Will be at his office to discuss Sanborn's letter.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, March 3, 1865; 8x5; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, Penna., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Did not look him up in Philadelphia, but now forgets the reason. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, March 27, 1865; 8x5; Jay, Charles A.
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Forwards papers but cannot forward fragment of meteorite.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, March 29, 1865; 8x5; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Sends letter from Sanborn.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, March 30, 1865; 6-1/2x4; Crowell, James M.
    A.L.S. 4p.and add. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Did not write the sermon he preached at the death of Sharswood, Sr. Gives his reasons for speaking extemporaneously.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, May 24, 1865; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1822-1908
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...;1865-1867.) Has no copy of his paper on metals left which he could send.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, May 24, 1865; 8x5; Jay, Charles A.
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Cannot obtain a piece of the meteorite.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, June 26, 1865; 7x5; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, A.L.S.with monogram. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Will be at home when he calls.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, July 10, [1865?]; 8x5; Jackson, Charles T., (Charles Thomas), 1805-1880
    A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) His plans for the summer. Concerning a meteorite.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Aug. 4, 1865; 8x5; Barden, Edward E.
    Rockport, Mass., A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning minerals and will exchange them.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Aug. 29, 1865; 10x8; LeConte, John, 1818-1891
    Columbia, S.C., A.L.S. 2p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning the aftermath of the war. FILM 403 FRAME 166
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Aug. 31, 1865; 8x6-1/2; Barden, Edward E.
    Rockport, Mass., A.L.S. 4p. (see W. Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning minerals.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Oct. 28, 1865; 8x5; Jackson, Charles T., (Charles Thomas), 1805-1880
    Boston, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Has been to Nevada and California. Refers to Humboldt. Cannot send a piece of his meteorite.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Nov. 7, 1865; 10x8; Brewer, N.
    Annapolis, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning positions for St. John's college.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Dec. 18, 1865; 10x8; Brewer, N.
    Annapolis, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Dr. Henry Barnard is principal of St. John's college and should be seen for positions.
  - Letter to [William] Sharswood, 1865-1867; 5-1/2x3-1/2; Allen, George, 1808-1876
    Saturday P.M. A.L.S. 3p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks for his publication.
  - Letters from various persons, 1865-1867; Sharswood, William, 1836-1905
    D. 98 items, with 2 broadsides. Various sizes. Presented by Miss. Frances Linchten; March 23, 1959. Table of contents available.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Jan. 25, 1866; 10x8; LeConte, John, 1818-1891
    Columbia, S.C., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Is trying to get the University of South Carolina open. Concerning his family.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Sharswood, Feb. 8, [1866]; 7-1/4x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Pittsburgh, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Sharswood, Philadelphia, Feb. 10, 1866; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Brewer, N.
    Annapolis, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning St.John's college and Dr. Barnard.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Feb. 18, [1866]; 7-1/2x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Cincinatti, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Feb. 21, 1866; 8x5-1/4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, Penna., A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...;1865-1867.) Concerning his plans. Concerning a possible gift of his publications to St. John's college.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Feb. 24, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Pearce, James
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning a theme for music.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Feb. 28, 1866; 8x5; Wilson, Rathwell
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning the disposal of a library and the possible gift of books to St.John's library.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], March 5, [1866]; 8x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Louisville, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], March 13, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning a visit with Dr. Barnard.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Philadelphia, March 20, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S.with initials. 2p.and add. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning Barnard's visit.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, March 26, 1866; 8x5; Putnam, F. W., (Frederic Ward), 1839-1915
    Salem, Mass., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning the Essex institute and mineralogy.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], March 26, [1866]; 7-1/2x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Nashville, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], April 19, 1866; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Haldeman, J. S.
    Harrisburg, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks him for publications.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, April 23, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning Barnard's visit.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], April 27, 1866; 4x2-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S.with monogram. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Is going abroad and does not care for letters when travelling.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, May 12, 1866; 8x6-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S.with initials. 1p.and add. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Is going abroad next week.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, May 29, 1866; 10x8; Brewer, N.
    Annapolis, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning a proposed gift of scientific apparatus for St. John's college.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], May 31, 1866; 8x5; Everett, William, 1839-1910
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Wishes the publication sent him had turned up.
  - Letter to [William] Sharswood, June 6, 1866; 8x5; Everett, William, 1839-1910
    Winchester, Mass., A.L.S. 4p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning their publications. Concerning St.John's college.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], June 19, 1866; 7-3/4x5; Graham, Mary
    Columbia, S.C., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867). Asks for publications pertaining to John L. LeConte.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], June 25, 1866; 8x5, 2-1/2x5; LeConte, Josephine
    Columbia, S.C., A.L.S.with initials. 5p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks for his publication. Concerning Reconstruction.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Sharswood, June 28, 1866; 8x5; Dickson, Samuel Henry, 1798-1872
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Will see him if he still wishes to visit.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Philadelphia, June 30, 1866; 8x5; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning sources of printed material about him. Refers to A.D.Bache.
  - Letter to [William] Sharswood, July 5, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Everett, William, 1839-1910
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Has corresponded with Barnard. Concerning publications.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, July 20, 1866; 7x4-1/2; Haldeman, J. S.
    Harrisburg, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thinks that through his friend's influence, he can get the post of Secretary of the Legation in Stockholm.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Sharswood, July 27, 1866; 8x5; McNarra, Edward
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning a possible diplomatic post.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, July 31, 1866; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Thayer, W. D.
    A.L.S. 1P. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning Legal matters.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Aug. 1, 1866; 8x5-1/4; Everett, William, 1839-1910
    Boston, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter. Does not wish his college "triumphs" noted.
  - Letter to [William] Sharswood, Aug. 6, 1866; 7x4-1/4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Has received his letters. Did not think he had gone abroad.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Aug. 9, 1866; 7-3/4x5; Boker, George H. (George Henry), 1823-1890
    A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks for his publication.
  - Letter to Guilielmo [William] Sharswood, Aug. 18, 1866; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Bianconi(?), Jo. Jos.
    L. 4p. In Italian. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.)
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Aug. 23, 1866; 8x5; Barden, Edward E.
    Rockport, Mass., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning minerals and Tufts college.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Aug. 23, 1866; 8x5; De Bow, J. D. B. (James Dunwoody Brownson), 1820-1867
    Nashville, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Does not pay for articles he publishes.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Aug. 28, 1866; 7-1/4x4-3/4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, Penna., A.L.S. 3p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning his future. Would not publish his correspondence with St.John's college.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Sept. 10, 1866; 7-1/2x5; De Bow, J. D. B. (James Dunwoody Brownson), 1820-1867
    Nashville, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letter...; 1865-1867.) Cannot purchase his article.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Sept. 14, 1866; 8x5; Barden, Edward E.
    Rockport, Mass., A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Will be very happy to exchange minealogical specimens.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Sept. 20, 1866; 6-1/2x4-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning his plans for teaching. Concerning possible publication by Sharswood in Vienna.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Oct. 2, 1866; 8x5; Barden, Edward E.
    Rockport, Mass., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Is sending him a box of mineralogical specimens from Rockport.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Oct. 2, 1866; 6-1/2x4-1/4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 2p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning his research and publications.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Nov. 23, 1866; 5-1/2x4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Will be in Philadelphia Monday or Tuesday.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Dec. 14, 1866; 8x5; Putnam, F. W., (Frederic Ward), 1839-1915
    Salem, Mass., A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Asks if he has received publication yet. Would like list of German names.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Feb. 19, 1867; 9x7; Bourne, John
    London, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks for his publication. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], March 19, 1867; 10-1/4x8-1/4; Vienna. Nationalbibliothek
    Vienna, L. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks for package of books.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, March 21, 1867; 7-1/4x4-3/4; Shephard, Charles Upham, 1804-1886
    Amherst, A.L.S. 2p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning minerals.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, April 10, 1867; 7-3/4x5; Allibone, S. Austin (Samuel Austin), 1816-1889
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Is not stereotyped after letter O.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], May 15, 1867; 8x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Bloomington, Ill., A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Wonders at his long silence. Thought she might act in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, May 16, 1867; 8x5; Smith, John Ford
    A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) No more explorers can be taken along.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], June 1, 1867; 8x5-1/4; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Louisville, Ky., A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Goes to Buffalo for two months.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], June 10, 1867; 8x5; White, Charles Abiathar, 1826-1910
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Cannot supply report requested.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], June 25, 1867; 9x5-1/2; Rungabe, A. R.
    Washington, L. 2p. In French. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Thanks for his publication. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, June 26, 1867; 8x5; Jefferis, William W.
    West Chester, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning mineralogy.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, July 12, 1867; 10x8; Beckel, Charles F.
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Forwards photograph.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, July 25, 1867; 8x5; Sanborn, Francis G.
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning his collection of insects which were meant for J.L.LeConte's study.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Aug. 12, [1867]; 8-1/4x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Buffalo, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter. Begins acting tours next month.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Sept. 1, 1867; 10x8, 6x8; LeConte, John, 1818-1891
    Columbia, S.C. A.L.S. 5p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning Reconstruction.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Sept. 20, 1867; 7x5-1/4; Franchenstein, baron de
    A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood Letters.. .; 1865-1867.) Suggests that he write the American legation in Vienna.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Sept. 20, [1867]; 7-1/2x5; Hosmer, Jean, 1842-1890
    Buffalo, A.L.S. 3p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Friendly letter. Concerning plays.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Sept. 21, 1867; 8x5-1/4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, Penna., A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867) Concerning a possible college of chemistry.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Sept. 22, 1867; 10x8; LeConte, John, 1818-1891
    Columbia, S.C., A.L.S. 4p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning education in the U.S.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Oct. 29, 1867; 7-3/4x5; Hay, John, 1838-1905
    Vienna, A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharswood Letters...; 1865-1867.) Has forwarded note as requested.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Nov. 6, 1867; 8x5; Ames, Fred L.
    A.L.S. 1p. (see W.Sharwood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Has forwarded letter.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Philadelphia, Nov. 7, 1867; 10x7-3/4; Browne, John Ross, 1817-1875
    Washington, A.L.S. 4p. (see W.Sharswood. Letter...; 1865-1867.) Concerning chemistry and mining schools
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Nov. 7, 1867; 6-1/2x4-1/4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, Penna., A.L.S. 1p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) States when he will be in and describes how to arrive at his home.
  - Letter to [William] Sharswood, Philadelphia, Nov. 13, 1867; 8x5; Smith, R. S. (Richard Somers), 1813-1877
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Enjoyed the use of music.
  - Letter to William Sharswood, Philadelphia, Nov. 13, 1867; 10-1/4x8-1/4; Toomy, Henry
    Munich, A.L.S. 1p. (see W. Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Forwarded publication as requested.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Sharswood, Philadelphia, Nov. 20, 1867; 10x7-3/4; Browne, John Ross, 1817-1875
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. (see W.Sharswood. Letters...; 1865-1867.) Concerning the establishment of a mining school.
  - Letter to [William Sharswood], Nov. 29, 1867; 8-3/4x5-1/2; Munich. Bayerische Staatsbibliothek